בוקר טוב, Boker tov, scratch,
today's דף daf is נ"ח Nun Chet and we start at the
very bottom of נ"ז עמוד ב' Nun Zayin Amud Bet in the
גמרא Gemara and now we are really getting into the practical aspects
about how the counting was done and we learned in the משנה
Mishna that there were three גורנות. granot. Now a גורן goran is
of course a threshing floor, so you can already see that we
are using the analogy of תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u'Ma'asrot for this, that
we add the same way in תרומות ומעשרות Terumot u'Ma'asrot you actually
have this primarily about wheat and about your threshing floor and about
times when you harvest, so here that analogy is being used. Now
as we will see in the גמרא, Gemara, why this is all
already, you know, this reflects the reality that I didn't, I have
to admit I did not check this on Wikipedia or other external
sources, but it reflects the reality that, you know, that animals as
opposed to humans, almost all animals don't copulate at all times. They're
only in heat at certain times and that there are different stages
in which you, you know, can predict that there's going to be
births amongst your flock. So reflecting those different birth periods, spring,
you know, sort of at the end of the fall and the
spring, at the end of the summer and so on, there are
these three different times
in which you do מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Behema. And again I assume
Michael explained but I'll just review, there are two primary הלכות Halachot
for designating these times. Most of the debate in the משנה Mishna
is what those times are. But there are two primary הלכות. Halachot.
One primary הלכה Halacha is that as opposed to מעשר Ma'aser with
grain, by מעשר Ma'aser with grain unless until you take תרומות ומעשרות
Terumot u'Ma'asrot it's טבל Tevel and you do a biblical prohibition, a
very weighty biblical prohibition if you eat it without taking it. But
that's not true with the case of מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Behema. In
theory it's just a מצוה, mitzvah, מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behema, it does
not make your flock טבל. Tevel. So in theory you could eat
all the flock or use them and never do it and all
you would have done, thank you, is not have done the מצוה.
mitzvah. You would not have violated any other prohibition, you just wouldn't
have done the מצוה. mitzvah. But חז"ל Chazal wanted to make it
more like מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behema, מעשר Ma'aser of grain, possibly because
of the parallel but more probably in order to give you an
incentive to make sure you did it. So they said at these
three times of the year, once those times arrive, you are not
allowed to eat or שחט shechter from the flock until you actually,
it's a type of a טבל Tevel rabbinically until you actually take
the מעשר. Ma'aser. That's the primary function of that. The other function
is, and this is not about all three of those times but
about the ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. What is the ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah for מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behema is a dividing line. Now we
learned you can't take from last year's on this year's, those have
to be separate and that is only one point which is the
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and in the משנה Mishna as we'll see
it spelled out in the גמרא, Gemara, it is argued whether that
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul or
whether that ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is ראש חודש תשרי Rosh Chodesh
Tishrei for מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Behema. So that is dividing when you
can, that you cannot take from one on the other, you also
don't group them to make a ten. Okay, so two separate הלכות.
Halachot. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Three lines from
the bottom on נ"ז עמוד ב'. Nun Zayin Amud Bet. מאי שנא
תלת? Mai shna tlat?
So now the גמרא, Gemara, some of what I just said will
be spelled out. Why are there these three times? אמר רבא בר
שילא, Amar Rava bar Shila, right, three different times in which you
do the, in which it's טבל Tevel until you actually separate it.
So אמר רבא בר שילא Amar Rava bar Shila לקבל lekabel means
like parallel to חרפי churfi the early, ואפלי ve'afli the late, וקיטי
ve'kayiti and the summer. So there would be three birthing periods amongst
the animals. And again, like I said, because the animals only copulate
when they're in heat. So there would be the early ones which
would give birth around פסח Pesach time, a little before פסח Pesach
time, the late ones which would give birth about, you know, two
months later around שבועות Shavuot time, and then the summer, the ones
that would be born after
the summer which would be right before סוכות. Sukkot. So those are
those three times.
ומאי שנא בהני זמני? U'mai shna behani zimni? So why specifically these
times? Meaning it doesn't mean roughly these seasons, that is exactly what
we already said. But why are there all these debates of exactly
this date, exactly that date?
Meaning how did you identify those precise dates and why are they
debated? So let's take a look. אמר רבי תנחום בריה דרבי חייא
איש כפר עכו, Amar Rabbi Tanchum brei de'Rabbi Chiya ish Kfar Akko,
so רבי תנחום Rabbi Tanchum said the following, כדי, kedei, top of
נ"ח עמוד א', Nun Chet Amud Aleph, כדי שתהא בהמה מצויה לעולי
רגלים, kedei she'tehei behema metzuya le'olei regalim,
in order that there be a lot of animals when it's the
time of the רגל. regel. Now obviously, right, that should be pretty
evident from the משנה. Mishna. The fact that we said fifteen days
before סוכות, Sukkot, fifteen days before, well פרוס, pros, I assume it
was explained that means fifteen, fifteen days, you didn't do that? Okay.
Anyway, a period before פסח, Pesach, a period before סוכות, Sukkot, a
period before שבועות Shavuot shows that it's related to the three רגלים.
regalim. And therefore the first interpretation of the גמרא Gemara is yes,
fundamentally this is the period when they're giving birth but we also
tied it into the רגלים. regalim. Why?
Now what you could have said is look, if you have to
bring your מעשר בהמה... Ma'aser Behema... up for a קרבן, Korban, we
might as well be nice to you. We might as well say,
do it at a time, the easier you make it for people,
the more they'll do it. So, do it at a time when
you're anyway going up two weeks later
for the רגל Regel and bringing your קרבנות Korbanot then, and then
if you have your מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah two weeks beforehand, then
people will do it more because they have to go up to
ירושלים Yerushalayim anyway, I might as well bring my מעשר בהמה Maaser
Behemah and I'll have more meat to eat, etc., etc. That's what
I would have imagined that the גמרא Gemara would have said, focusing
on me having my מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah and just making it
easier for me to bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. The גמרא Gemara
doesn't say that. The גמרא Gemara says if I am waiting to
take מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah until that time, then I am not
going to be שחט shechting my sheep prior to that time because
I want to wait, I'm not doing anything with my sheep or
my cattle until I take מעשר בהמה. Maaser Behemah. So then two
weeks before פסח, Pesach, two weeks before סוכות, Succos, I've got all
of these young calves, all of these young sheep that are in
my flock because I haven't done anything with them, I waited until
I took מעשר בהמה, Maaser Behemah, and everybody else is coming up
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so they're going to want to be buying calves
and sheep for A, for meat, B, for קרבנות, Korbanot, and I'm
going to have a lot of them available, so everybody wins. I
hold off on doing anything with them because I'm taking מעשר, Maaser,
then I have a lot of them available, everybody's coming up. Now
that's for the people in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? I mean, that's sort
of the irony here. Who are the people that are having this
cattle and sheep available? It's only the people in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It
doesn't really explain why when you're coming from other places how holding
off on the מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah helps. But that's the גמרא's
Gemara answer. Now the obvious question you should ask is, wait
a minute, the משנה Mishna just said that you're allowed to שחט
shecht and to use them prior to these periods. So if a
person is totally focused on their own self-interest, what they're going to
say is, oh my gosh, it's coming up to be that period
before פסח, Pesach, I better start שחט shechting my sheep and selling
them and selling the meat now so that I don't have so
much מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah to take in a few days from
now. So you understand? Right? When it comes to this period, what's
the הלכה? halacha? Until this period arrives, you can שחט shecht your
meat, you can sell it, you can do whatever you want with
it. Once this period arrives, you have to take מעשר בהמה. Maaser
Behemah. So if you're not so interested in the מצוה, mitzvah, if
you're totally focused on your own self-interest, then what are you going
to do? You're going to try to work really hard to sell
all your stuff to a butcher or to eat it yourself so
that you have much less to take מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah on
before that time arrives. So it's actually the exact opposite. Once that
time arrives, there's very little meat available. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, actually we're here going to assume that people are going to
be properly motivated even though out of self-interest it would have led
to the opposite result.
Well, let's read הנה, hinei, the one thing they didn't address
in,
except from what
you know, is maybe because of the fact that the קרבן Korban
is needed by so many people, it might push up the demand
so much that the more I have, the more money I'll make.
So you may end up coming out ahead.
Even, that could be, but then it would have to do with
the fact that we established the מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah at that
period. That might be anyway if you're a smart businessman.
But that's okay, but that's not related to our question, which is
why we designated these times for מעשר בהמה. Maaser Behemah. So let's
read it, the גמרא Gemara says,
ואף על גב דתנן, ve'af al gav detnan, although a משנה Mishna
said that you could do the exact opposite, עד שלא הגיע הגורן
מותר למכור ולשחוט, ad shelo higia hagoren mutar limkor ulishchot, that you
can שחט shecht and sell before. So if you're really focused on
your self-interest, you'll just try really to get rid of it before
that period and have the exact opposite effect. So nevertheless, ניחא ליה
לאיניש ניחא ליה דליעביד מצוה בממוניה. nichla lei le'inish nichla lei deleivid
mitzvah bemamonei.
People would rather, people want to do a מצוה. mitzvah. And so
this is interesting in terms of the גמרא's Gemara sense about religious
psychology. It's like you probably only wake up to the fact that
it's מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah time a week or two in advance,
and then you figure, here we're actually going to assume people are
going to have like the right type of religious motivation. It's coming
up in two weeks, I might as well just leave it and
wait and so on or therefore be able to do like a
lot of מעשר בהמה. Maaser Behemah. So again, it's pretty funny because
sometimes we assume the exact opposite, especially when it comes to financial
issues. Here we're saying that your mentality is going to be, you
know what, the period is coming up, I'm not going to שחט,
shecht, I'm not going to sell, I'm going to keep it all
around so that I'll be able to do the מצוה. mitzvah. And
therefore, if I'm leaving all my sheep around, it'll be available when
people come up for the רגל. Regel. So as I said, I
find this an interesting explanation because what I would have said is
what I told you, that first of all, the people bringing מעשר
בהמה Maaser Behemah are not just the people in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's
everybody in all of ישראל, Yisrael, perhaps everybody in חוץ לארץ Chutz
Laaretz as well. If you're, so I would have said, why do
you do it by the רגלים? Regalim? Because if I have to
anyway be עולה לרגל, oleh laregel, חז"ל Chazal might as well be
nice to me and I'll take מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah right before
then and I'll bring it up when I'm coming up לרגל laregel
and it'll make that much easier for me to do the מצוה
mitzvah and that much more willing to do the מצוה. mitzvah. Somehow
we ignore that, we focus on the fact that we want meat
available, which really focuses only on the people in ירושלים Yerushalayim and
the environment, I assume. And number two, we assert
that...
But I actually have one question on that. If you're going to
do an event, there's going to be a huge number of animals
to be eaten, particularly large animals.
Right, right,
right. Well, no, the animals I'm leaving over are the newborn ones.
Right, but the cows are pretty big.
Okay, but as long as they're under a year, I mean everybody
coming up has to bring an עולת ראיה, Olat Re'iyah, שלמי חגיגה.
Shalmei Chagigah.
So as Michael said, even the amount of meat the people are
going to be having... Right, but you can't shecht a קרבן Korban
and not eat it.
Right. No, but again, I'm sorry if I wasn't clear. The point
isn't that there's a lot of animals available because there's a lot
of מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Behemah. The מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behemah, I'm sorry
if that wasn't clear, the מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah is what I
have, what you know, I bring myself and I eat myself, and
then it's not like בהמות Behemot are מצוי, matzui, it's more like
בשר basar is מצוי matzui because I can ask people to join
me with my מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Behemah. No, the point is that
if I am, if we're assuming that I'm religiously motivated and therefore
I am not שוחט shochet and whatever in the months preceding in
order that I can do the full מצוה Mitzvah of מעשר בהמה
Ma'aser Behemah with all of my flock, that after I take my
מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behemah, I still have all of the rest of
my flock which I haven't used yet. And therefore people coming up
for the רגל Regel are going to want to buy it for
their obligatory קרבנות. Korbanot. Okay, so I'm sorry if that wasn't clear.
I mean, the animals that are found that are available now that
the גמרא Gemara is focusing on is not what I, the owner,
am bringing for my מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Behemah. I can share, happily
share the meat with that, but that's not animals for their קרבנות.
Korbanot. What's available is that because I wanted to do מעשר בהמה
Ma'aser Behemah the best way, in the full way, I was not
שוחט shochet the other animals. And the other animals are now, I
have my full flock available now to be sold to people that
are coming up for the רגל. Regel.
מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah is effectively a שלמים, Shelamim, right?
Yeah,
in the way it's offered. Right, right.
No, but if the price of animals by רגל Regel is higher...
Well, that's what I said.
That's what Michael said, but then you know, so it's good for
the עולי רגלים, Olei Regalim, but it's not so good for the
sellers. You know, you really have to talk about because, right, because
then the market is like glutted now, you know, or like whatever,
there's a high, better for the sellers for it to be high
demand and low supply. Now what we're trying to introduce is high
demand and high supply. So anyway, alright, let's continue in the גמרא.
Gemara. But anyway, that's how the גמרא Gemara explains why it's tied
to the רגלים. Regalim. וכמה פרס? V'kamah Pras? And how, I'm sorry,
ומה קרי ליה גורן? U'mah kari lei Goren? Why do they call
it a threshing floor? דתבלו כגורן, D'tavlu k'Goren, because it's a parallel
to the wheat that we rabbinically say that you can't eat from
it until you take מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Behemah. וכמה פרס? V'kamah Pras?
How many days is פרס, Pras, which literally means a half? פירש
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אין פרס פחות מט"ו יום, Peirash Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehudah ein Pras pachot mi'tet-vav yom, 15 days. מאי משמע? Mai
mashma? Where do you get that? אמר רבי אבהו פרוס. Amar Rabbi
Abbahu Pros. פרוס Pros means like a portion or פלגא, palga, half.
פלגא דמאי? Palga d'mai? Half of what? פלגא דהלכות פסח, Palga d'hilchot
Pesach, half of the time period that precedes the רגל Regel when
you're supposed to be learning about the laws of the רגל. Regel.
כי הא דתניא, Ki ha d'tanya, like we taught, שואלים ודורשים בהלכות
הפסח קודם הפסח שלשים יום, sho'alin v'dorshin b'hilchot ha'Pesach kodem ha'Pesach shloshim
yom, that you, you know, you give classes and you learn the
laws relating to פסח. Pesach. Now there's a question in general whether
this is relating to the חג Chag or to relating to the
קרבנות Korbanot of the חג, Chag, but be that as it may,
you start דורש dorshing about the הלכות halachot and talking about the
הלכות halachot 30 days before. So the period before, there's assumed to
be like this conceptual month's period prior to the רגל, Regel, and
פרס Pras means half of that period, 15 days. Okay, so that's
what, so for 15, so therefore when we want to say 15
days before the חג, Chag, we say פרוס הפסח, Pros ha'Pesach, פרוס
עצרת. Pros Atzeret. So somewhere measurement also...
There's a, there's a, yeah, there's a פרסה. Parsah. Yeah, okay. So,
okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר
שתי שבתות,
v'Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer shtei shabatot,
and within that question about how long you start דורש, dorshing, he
says two weeks, which is 14 days, not 15, but we're going
to bracket that, we'll get back to that later. So now we
have, so that's the first opinion. You focus three periods of the
year animal gives birth, you focus on the רגלים Regalim the way
the גמרא Gemara explains it so that you're holding off giving your
מעשר Ma'aser though you don't have to, you're a good guy, you're
holding off giving your מעשר Ma'aser until that period so then a
lot of the rest of your flock is available for עולי רגלים.
Olei Regalim. And what's that period? 15 days before each רגל. Regel.
Now we go to the other opinions. בן עזאי אומר בכ"ט באדר
באחד בסיון. Ben Azzai omer b'chaf-tet b'Adar b'echad b'Sivan. So בן עזאי
Ben Azzai says 29th of אדר, Adar, the first of סיון, Sivan,
and the... what else did he say? And the 29th of אב.
Av. So let's take a look. Some of those seem pretty close
to what we said before, but some not. So במאי קמיפלגי רבי
עקיבא ובן עזאי? B'mai kamiflagi Rabbi Akiva u'Ben Azzai? What's their debate?
רבי עקיבא סבר אדר הסמוך לניסן זימנין מלא וזימנין חסר. Rabbi Akiva
savar Adar ha'samuch l'Nissan zimnin malei v'zimnin chaser. So if you, so
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says I'm not going to give you an
exact date when I say 15 days before because you don't know
the preceding month whether it's going to be מלא malei or
חסר, chaser, right, whether it's going to be a 29 or 30
day month. So I'm just going to tell you 15 days before,
I can't fix it on a calendar date.
So therefore זימנין דמיקרי ביום ל' זימנין בכ"ט. zimnin d'mikrei b'yom lamed
zimnin b'chaf-tet.
Sometimes therefore 15 days will be the 30th, sometimes it'll be the
29th. Now how does that work, by the way, if you want
to think about it? So if פסח Pesach is the 15th, right,
there are 14 days
is מלא, malei, then the 15 days before is the 30th of
אדר. Adar. If it's חסר, chaser, then it's the 29th of אדר.
Adar. But it goes one day into the previous month. That's what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. ומשום הכי לא קבע ליה זמן, u'mishum
hachi lo kava lei zman, therefore he didn't give you a date,
he just said 15 days before. ובן עזאי סבר אדר הסמוך לניסן
לעולם חסר, u'Ben Azzai savar Adar ha'samuch l'Nissan l'olam chaser, basically he
agrees with the idea of the 15 days before, but he happens
to hold that אדר Adar is always a 29-day month. And therefore,
הלכך קבע ליה זמן בכ"ט באדר, hilkach kava lei zman b'chaf-tes b'Adar,
therefore he's prepared just to say the 29th of אדר, Adar, because
basically it's 15 days but applied to an assumption that אדר Adar
is only 29 days. Okay, that's their 29th אדר, Adar, there they
basically agree that it's just a question about fixing the date. Now
how about the other opinion? באחד בסיון, b'echad b'Sivan, first of סיון,
Sivan, that's no 15 days before שבועות, Shavuot, that's like six days
before שבועות, Shavuot, five days before
שבועות. Shavuot. So אידי דלא נפישי, idi d'lo nefishei, because there's not
a lot of time between פסח Pesach and שבועות, Shavuot, how many
new flock are being born in the next seven weeks? Right, not
too many. Now obviously it doesn't have to mean that they're getting
pregnant those seven weeks, but you know, but basically the primary birthing
season at the springtime was ניסן. Nissan. So anything that they're giving
birth now seven weeks, you know, in the next seven weeks are
just the stragglers. There's not so many more flock that are going
to be born.
And it doesn't fit in with the שבעה עשר?
shiva asar? So that's the point. So we still want there to
be a lot available, but we also acknowledge that there's going to
be a lot less. So we're trying to do everything we can
to maximize how much is available. And therefore we're giving you more
time. אי אמרת לקדם לעשר, ei amart l'akdem l'aser,
so if you say take מעשר ma'aser early by the 15, you
know, 15 days before, there's so little to start with, you're taking
מעשר, ma'aser, then they're going to and after they take the מעשר,
ma'aser, they're going to start שחט shachting and eating the meat. So
there's so so therefore אדמטי רגלא שלמי להו, ad'mati ragla shalmi lehu,
by the time the רגל regel rolls around, they're going to have,
you know, there's not going to be so much meat available. So
because there's much less flock in general in that intermediate period, we
want to postpone the taking of מעשר ma'aser as late as possible
so that the maximum amount of that little flock is going to
be available. So that's why he said it. בכ"ט באב. b'chaf-tes b'Av.
Anyway,
in the 29th of אב, Av, what's that about? Now that obviously
is not 15 days before before the רגל, regel, 15 days before
the רגל regel is before סוכות Sukkot is ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
or the last day of אלול. Elul. What's what's the 29th of
אב? Av? That's, you know, a good month earlier. So בכ"ט
באב, b'chaf-tes b'Av, then בן עזאי לטעמיה, Ben Azzai l'taamei, Ben Azzai
is according to his reasoning at the end of the משנה, Mishnah,
דאמר האלולין מתעשרין בפני עצמן, d'amar ha'Elulin mitasrin bifnei atzman, the ones
that are born in אלול, Elul, you take your own מעשר ma'aser
from them. So meaning why? Meaning as we're going to see in
the גמרא, Gemara, okay, as I said the bigger dividing line is
not just the גורן, goren, גזונטהייט, gezuntheit, the bigger dividing line is
when is ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So whatever the ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah is for the sheep, you can't take from one year on
the next. So some say ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is אלול, Elul,
some say ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, some say it's ראש
חודש תשרי. Rosh Chodesh Tishrei. בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, as will be
explained, is not sure who to פסקן pasken like, whether it's ראש
חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul or ראש חודש תשרי. Rosh Chodesh Tishrei.
So what are you going to do? What the stuff that's born
during אלול, Elul, do you take them, גזונטהייט, gezuntheit, with the stuff
from before, or do you take them with the stuff after? You
can't take them with the stuff before, maybe ראש חודש אלול Rosh
Chodesh Elul was the dividing line. You can't take them with the
stuff born in תשרי, Tishrei, maybe ראש חודש תשרי Rosh Chodesh Tishrei
was the dividing line. The only choice you have is to take
all the אלול Elul flock on its own, but you can't combine
it with what's before, what's after, because you don't know where the
dividing line is. One second. So since that's בן עזאי's Ben Azzai
position, he cannot allow the threshing floor, the גורן, goren, to go
into אלול, Elul, right? Because if it goes into אלול, Elul, you're
combining stuff that might be over the dividing line with stuff that's
before the dividing line. So when he makes his threshing floors, as
it were, it has to be before אלול Elul so you don't
co-mix what might be two different הלכה, halacha, two different years. בכ"ט
באב. b'chaf-tes b'Av. Yeah.
So let's
just so let's just read that.
Rabbi Michael says it correctly because essentially what he's going to do
is he's going to take then on כ"ט chaf-tes of אדר Adar
and then he's going to take on כ"ט chaf-tes of אלול, Elul,
right? Because he's going to do the אלולs Elul by themselves. So
basically you have to make the dividing line the last day of
אב Av and then you have to make another dividing line the
last day of אלול Elul in order because you don't know how
to group the אלול. Elul. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says,
I'll take it in a second. The גמרא Gemara says like this:
so therefore
ולאשמעינן ביום ל', v'lashmieinan b'yom lamed, so then the only question the
גמרא Gemara is left with is how about on day 30 of
אב? Av? Because אב Av has 30 has, you know, assuming אב
Av has 30 days. So therefore day 30 of אב Av is
really the last day. Why do we do day 29 of אב?
Av? So the גמרא Gemara says no, זימנין דמחסר, zimnin d'mchasar, I'm
saying אדר, Adar, I meant אב, Av, I'm sorry. I'm sorry. So
right, so אב Av has usually has 30 days, so why not
do it on the 30th day of אב? Av? because that's really
the last day. זמנין דמחסרי ליה לאב, Zimnin demachasrei leh le'av, sometimes
אב Av actually does have only 29. ובדין למעבד הכירא בחדש וישן
Ubidinn leme'avad hikera bechodesh viyashan and you want a clear dividing line.
What does that mean? It means if we tell people take it
on day 30 of אב, Av,
so in fine, nine years out of ten it would be fine,
but on the one year that the day 30 of אב Av
is ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, people are going to take
on ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul for the stuff before. And
then that's going to confuse them because that's going to sort of
send the signal that you can actually combine אלול Elul and אב.
Av. And that's something we have to be very careful about because
that might be a hard dividing line. So in order not to
confuse people, right, to have it possible that once you're actually taking
מעשר ma'aser on the other on the pre-אלול Elul stuff in אלול
Elul itself, we're going to say do it on the 29th. Because
the 29th is always אב. Av.
Right.
So yeah, for whatever reason, you're right, they they one
day before the season.
I I understand, I understand. But the point is somehow people would
people wouldn't get that, they have to put it in their Outlook
calendar and they have to pick an exact date. So anyway, so
therefore they say better to do it on the 29th because if
you do it on the 30th, sometimes you'll be co-mixing. Now רש"י
Rashi says one second, that you're not actually going to co-mix because
if anything was born on ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, you're
not taking מעשר ma'aser on it. It's not yet eight days old,
right? You don't take מעשר ma'aser on stuff less than eight days
old. So we're not afraid you're actually going to co-mix. But what
we are afraid of is that you'll send a wrong signal, that
people will actually think or you yourself will begin to think that
you can combine אב Av actually yeah, אב Av and אלול. Elul.
Yeah, but Charlie's point is people who are not close to ירושלים
Yerushalayim are not going to know whether the day is ראש חודש
אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul or 29.
No, you will by the end of the month. By the end
of the month you will have found out when the oh oh
how you're right, no I'm sorry, you're absolutely right. You'll know when
the pre when the previous month was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh but
not the coming month. Right. So that's a good point too, but
that's reinforcing it. Exactly. So that you will so that answers Michael's
question. Thank you. Meaning you'll have done 30 because you normally are
doing 30 and that's the standard and then you'll find out three
weeks later that it was whatever. Right. That's an excellent point.
So the second thing is this is this actually creating a leniency
because if you don't have nine animals, right, for the month of
אלול, Elul, you aren't going to tithe anything. Right. And you're getting
you're exempting yourself. So this is a huge leniency for small farmers.
You mean the general point that you do the אלולין בפני עצמן?
alulin bifnei atzman? Yes. And that is true. But as we're going
to see in the גמרא, Gemara, there's a principle that מעשר ודאי
אמר רחמנא ולא מעשר ספק. ma'aser vadai amrachmana velo ma'aser safek. So
since any time there's a doubt you wouldn't take about whether you
take מעשר, ma'aser, you don't take מעשר. ma'aser. So since בן עזאי
Ben Azzai is saying halachically I don't know whether it goes in
the previous year or the following year, so those all are scenarios
of מעשר ספק. ma'aser safek. But you're right, it means that most
you might very well get out of, you know, of taking מעשר
ma'aser for those אלול Elul for that אלול Elul flock. And it
also might get you out of stuff from the previous because you
could have had nine animals beforehand and one more during אלול Elul
and nine after, and because each one is a ספק, safek, you
don't wind up taking for any. You're absolutely correct about that. Okay.
All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים
באחד בניסן ובאחד בסיון. Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Shimon omrim be'echad beNissan uve'echad
beSivan. So they have a similar position except rather than saying
the 29th of אדר, Adar, they say באחד בניסן. be'echad beNissan. So
let's take a look. באחד בניסן Be'echad beNissan to רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. So how does he get that? That's only 14 days before,
not 15. Ah, because they also follow this model about דורשים dorshim
about the period of when you start learning about the הלכות halachot
beforehand as like the period prior to. But rather than using the
15-day model, which is half of the 30, they use the 14-day
model. Just like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel דאמר שתי שבתות. de'amar shtei
shabbatot. He says that when do you start learning about the הלכות?
halachot? Two weeks before, not 30 days before. So everybody wants is
going to use this as a model because this idea of when
you start learning the הלכות, halachot, that defines the period leading up
to the חג. chag. But within that, you can sort of do
the 30 day and say half of that or you can do
the 14, so that's a difference of one day.
15 and 14.
Yeah, that's true. Because everybody roughly wanted it at that time and
that's why they wanted to use like a standard measure. So there
are two standard measures, פרוס pros and 14, you know, which are
only different by a day. Okay. באחד בסיון Be'echad beSivan כדאמרן. kedamaran.
Why the first of סיון? Sivan? Like we said, because you want
to because even though you want to say two weeks beforehand, there's
so few flock that you want to maximize the amount that's available,
so you're postponing the מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah before שבועות. Shavuot. Okay.
בכ"ט באלול, Be'chaf tet be'Elul, the 29th of אלול. Elul. Now why
now that's the major shift from the previous position. The major shift
is the previous one said the 29th of אדר, Adar, this says
the 29th of אלול. Elul. I keep on doing that, of אב.
Av. This says the 29th of אלול. Elul. And the difference should
be obvious because this draws the dividing line not at ראש חודש
אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, but the dividing line at ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, ראש חודש תשרי. Rosh Chodesh Tishrei. So why בכ"ט באלול? be'chaf
tet be'Elul? רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון לטעמייהו, Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Shimon letamayhu,
they go according to their reasoning דאמרי באחד בתשרי ראש השנה למעשר
בהמה, de'amri be'echad beTishrei Rosh Hashanah lema'aser behemah, that the first of
תשרי. Tishrei. Okay, so there's a major question, obviously you're going to
do your גורן goren before that ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. There are
three separate... periods with the נפקא מינא nafka mina that you don't
take, you don't eat the animals once those periods arrive until you
do מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah, but one of those periods is the
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, which is a historical strong dividing line and
then you can't group anything prior to anything after. So for the
previous that dividing line was ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh Elul, so
it was the twenty-ninth of אב, Av, and here it's ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashanah, so it was the twenty-ninth of אלול. Elul. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara goes on. ולמה אמרו בכ"ט באלול ולא אמרו באחד
בתשרי? velama amru be-chaf-tes be-Elul velo amru be-echad be-Tishrei? Right?
I'm sure you found that interesting in the משנה Mishnah that you
learned yesterday, that whole sort of like reflection and why are we
saying this and you know, the משניות mishnayot here seem a little
more verbose at times than they do in other areas. But okay.
So it said מפני שהוא יום טוב, mipnei shehu Yom Tov, because
you can't do the מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah because it's יום טוב. Yom Tov. Why? We'll see in a
minute, but anyway, that's why we did it on the twenty-ninth rather
than on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So the גמרא Gemara says ותיפוק
ליה דבעינא למעבד היכירא בחדש וישן. ve-teipuk lei de-ba'ina le-me'avad hekera be-chodesh
ve-yashan. Why do you need to say that you can't do מעשר
בהמה ma'aser behemah on יום טוב? Yom Tov? There's a better reason.
If you can't mix pre-ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah with ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, so if you're going to do it on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah itself, you're commingling those periods. So again, even though רש"י Rashi
says you're not really commingling the animals because any animal born on
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is too young to do מעשר בהמה, ma'aser
behemah, but nevertheless, you don't want to be doing מעשר בהמה ma'aser
behemah of pre-ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. You're
sending a signal that those periods can be mixed. You have to
do it before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah arrives. So isn't that the
better reason? So the גמרא Gemara says חדא ועוד קאמר. chada ve-od
ka'amar. You're right. We're throwing in yet another reason. חדא, chada, number
one, the more primary reason which relates exactly to, you know, these
concerns, למעבד היכירא בחדש וישן, le-me'avad hekera be-chodesh ve-yashan, that you don't
want to, you want to make a very clear distinction, you don't
want to commingle the year prior to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah with
the year beginning on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, so you don't want
to do it on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah itself. And number two,
ועוד מפני שהוא יום טוב, ve-od mipnei shehu Yom Tov, ואי
אפשר
לעשר, ve-i efshar le-aser, you can't do מעשר ma'aser on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. Why not? מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? ביום טוב משום סיקרא,
be-Yom Tov mishum sikresta, because of the, of the paint, of the
staining. Meaning as we're going to learn in the next משנה, Mishnah,
the way you do מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah is you dip your,
your a staff in like red paint, the animals come out, or
and then when you get to number ten, you you hit it
with the staff and and you, you know, mark it. So therefore
you can't do that on יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's a type
of כתיבה ketiva or צביעה tzvia and so on. Now תוספות Tosafot
asks a better question. תוספות Tosafot says what do you mean? Isn't
there a more obvious reason why you can't do it on יום
טוב? Yom Tov? You're not allowed to להיות מקדיש lehiyot makdish things
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now, you're also can't take תרומות ומעשרות,
terumot u-ma'asrot, but there's the reason you can't take תרומות ומעשרות terumot
u-ma'asrot is because it looks like you're מתקן, metaken, because now it
makes the grain able to be eaten. Okay, תוספות Tosafot doesn't ask
that question because here, here, it's not really that the flock is
forbidden, the rabbis just say you're not allowed to, but it doesn't
matter. It's not like the flock is forbidden as איסור issur food.
It's like, it's more on the גברא gavra than on the animals.
You are not allowed to eat from it until you do this
מצוה. mitzvah. It's sort of like, not exactly, I mean it's an
interesting conceptual question like, you're not supposed to sit down to a
meal before you, before you hear a שופר, shofar, before you, before
you hear the מגילה, megilla, etc. So you know, you could focus
it totally on me, not on the animal. I'm not allowed to
eat from the flock until I do it. Now the גמרא Gemara
isn't, does use the phrase before that it's מטבלת, metavelet, טבל כהאי
גוונא. tevel ke-hai gavna. But I think that's an interesting question. When
the rabbis said don't eat from it, are they really saying it's
like forbidden food or are they just saying that I'm not supposed
to? So you could have asked the question that if they say
it's forbidden food then it's like you fixed the food, you fixed
the sheep by taking that. תוספות Tosafot doesn't ask that question, I
assume because either it's that aspect is only rabbinic and more and
and possibly because of what I said maybe it focuses less on
the sheep, more on me. But תוספות Tosafot does ask the question
that you're not allowed to sanctify things on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
That's a type of a transaction. You're giving it over to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you're sanctifying. How are you allowed to sanctify
here? And he goes through a couple of answers, none of which
he's happiest with, and then he says his last answer. And his
last answer seems to be the best and the one that he's
happiest with, which is: although מעשר ma'aser is not like בכור, bechor,
בכור bechor is קדוש kadosh automatically. מעשר ma'aser you have to count.
You don't actually have to instill sanctity and מקדיש makdish by מעשר.
ma'aser. All you have to do is say this is number ten.
And as soon as you say this is ten, one, two, three,
four, ten, you don't have to say I am now מקדיש makdish
this animal as מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. The fact that it's counted
as ten, it's, that, it, the קדושה kedusha gets instilled automatically. So
therefore it's not really an act, although it results in its קדושה,
kedusha, it's not an act of instilling קדושה, kedusha, it's only an
act of designating it as number ten. So that's why תוספות Tosafot
says the גמרא Gemara here had to say the only issue was
the, the paint and not these other things. So the reason I'm
spelling this out is it raises important conceptual questions about מעשר. ma'aser.
Number one is, when the rabbis said don't eat until I take
it, is it really איסור issur food? Is it really a sense
of fixing the flock? Okay, תוספות Tosafot doesn't even raise that question.
And the other issue is, am I really sanctifying the tenth or
am I just designating the tenth?
Yes. Dad, you may not want to answer this, but I can't
resist asking the question. First, see and it's more transactional based, and
how are you allowed to like let's say שמחה simcha on שבועות?
Shavuot? Isn't that the same thing?
Wait, wait, wait.
Or you
say
then if it's... but you're not actually sanctifying,
you're not actually transferring funds, okay? If you, you know, so, so
that, so which is when you're מקדיש, makdish, it's not just you're
talking about doing it, about your desire and about your commitment to
do it, you're actually, if you know, sanctifying and affecting it at
that moment. Yeah, Rivka.
It just brings to mind ונתנה תוקף, Unetanneh Tokef, מעביר צאנו תחת
שבטו. Ma'avir Tzono Tachat Shivto.
Right, well that's exactly where that comes from.
I had that in mind.
Absolutely. Right before ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Oh, that's interesting. Ah, that,
that I didn't connect. Meaning I, I always thought about that metaphor,
but you're right, the timing connects this
by saying that.
Right, that's a very beautiful point. Thank you. Yes.
But the גמרא's Gemara answer is you don't have to, there must
be an
alternative to using the red paint. Yes, so we're going to talk
about that in the next משנה. Mishnah. But the concern was, was
that if that's the way you standard do on the standard, maybe
you'll accidentally wind up doing it this way. Of course, if it's
only three times in a year when you do it and this
is one of the three, hopefully you could remember that this is
a different way. But so it's a good point, but you might
cook, you might think it's יום טוב. Yom Tov. I understand. Anyway,
but, but the other point is what the גמרא Gemara really says
is you don't even need this reason. The better reason is because
you don't want to commingle pre-ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah with ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah. Is there another question? Okay, so let's go on. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי מאיר אומר
באחד באלול ראש השנה למעשר בהמה. Rabbi Meir omer be-echad be-Elul Rosh
Hashanah le-ma'aser behemah. And now we have the explicit debate of what
is that real dividing line. Is it ראש חודש אלול? Rosh Chodesh
Elul? Is it אלול Elul by itself? Or is it ראש השנה?
Rosh Hashanah?
So תניא, Tanya, so we taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: אמר בן
עזאי. Amar Ben Azzai. So בן עזאי Ben Azzai said: הללו אומרים
כך והללו אומרים כך. Hallalu omrim kach ve-hallalu omrim kach. Since these
rabbis say אלול Elul and these rabbis say תשרי, Tishrei, so, so
what are we going to do? So אלולים מתעשרין לעצמן. Elulim mit'asrin
le-atzman. So we'll have to play it safe. So here's like a
first example of saying I'm not going to make a decision, be
מחמיר. machmir. Okay, but of course as was pointed out, it's not,
you know, it's not just a חומרא, chumra, it's also a קולא
kula because then you don't combine and you get out of מעשר
בהמה. ma'aser behemah. But he's saying I don't know how to פסקן,
pasken, so we have to play it safe. How that means you
get off, maybe you are חייב, chayav, so that's what I mentioned,
the principle that מעשר ודאי ולא מעשר ספק. ma'aser vadai velo ma'aser
safek. So once I believe I don't know how to פסקן pasken
and it's a ספק safek for me, I'm, so therefore I have
to treat it separately and the result is I don't take מעשר
ma'aser because, but you know, I don't combine it with the previous
and take מעשר ma'aser because that's מעשר ספק. ma'aser safek. Yes.
But בן עזאי Ben Azzai just said that he knows when it
is. So why isn't he following his own opinion?
Where did he say he knows when it is? When it says
אלולים בפני עצמן. Elulim bifnei atzman.
No, about the
day, about 29th of אב, Av, because whenever was
that something else.
No, that's once we're, we've decided you have to do it in
אלול Elul by itself, then we're going to...
In the משנה, Mishnah, בן עזאי Ben Azzai says
בעשרים ותשעה באב. be-esrim ve-tisha be-Av.
Not תשעה באב. Tisha be-Av. כ"ט באב. Kaf-tet be-Av. He said בעשרים
ותשעה באב. be-esrim ve-tisha be-Av. Right,
so, yes. Meaning I don't, he's saying I don't know if the
dividing line is ראש חודש אלול Rosh Chodesh Elul or ראש חודש
תשרי. Rosh Chodesh Tishrei. Therefore I'm going to set out אלול Elul
by itself. Now that I've set out אלול Elul by itself, you
take מעשר ma'aser on the 29th of אב. Av. Okay, so now
we're going to see why, why he can't make up his mind.
So let's take a look. וליחזי טעמא דמאן מסתבר, Velichzei ta'ama de-man
mistaber,
which is this like such a great distillation of the two basic
approaches to הלכה halakhah nowadays. The one that says ah, מחלוקת, machlokes,
be מחמיר. machmir. And the גמרא Gemara is not happy with that.
The גמרא Gemara says why don't you actually think about the different
positions and decide which one is right and פסקן. pasken. Don't say
I'm going to be מחמיר. machmir. פסקן, Pasken, make up your mind.
Okay, so let's see which position makes sense and decide. So the
גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא לא מצי קאי אטעמייהו, ve-chi teima lo
matzi kaya ata-maihu, let's say you say that he feels like he
can't decide, I'm sorry, that he can't decide, he, yeah,
meaning
he can't, he can't either know what their reason is or he
can't decide who has a more persuasive argument. How could you say
that? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Baraita: בן עזאי אומר
כל חכמי ישראל דומים עלי כקליפת השום. Ben Azzai omer kol chachmei
Yisrael domim elai ke-klipat ha-shum. All of the sages of Israel, they
know nothing compared to me. They're like the, like the shell of
a garlic. You know the shell, right,
a garlic, how thin that is, the peel, how thin
that is, they're, they're nothing to me. They're nothing
in terms of my intelligence. חוץ מן הקרח הזה, Chutz min ha-kereach
hazeh, except for this baldy.
Now who
is the baldy?
So רש"י Rashi says it's רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, he
was
bald. And רש"י Rashi actually goes further to say that רבי יהושע
בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha is רבי יהושע בן רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Rabbi Akiva because קרחה Korcha is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. תוספות Tosafot rejects this completely. First... proves out that רבי יהושע
בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Korcha could not have been רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva son based on the date. But number two, he said
why would he have referred to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva with such
a sort of like, you know, derogatory term, this baldy? So תוספות
Tosafos says, so תוספות Tosafos says two other opinions. Maybe it was
just some guy whose name was קרחה, Korcha, or maybe it was
another guy who was bald! But it's so funny, there's nobody knows
nothing except this baldy, we don't even know who he's talking about.
It still doesn't answer why he's talking about it in these negative
terminology. Anyway, so since בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, you know, certainly he
holds of himself as being more smarter than everyone else, so how
could he say I don't know who to פסקן pasken like? If
you're so smart, so make a decision! So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר יוחנן, Amar Yochanan, here's why not: מפי השמועה אמרוה, Mipi hashmua
amruha, מפי חגי זכריה מלאכי, Mipi Chagai Zecharia Malachi,
because he did not get it from a סברא, svara, they got
it from the נביאים. Neviim. Now what does this mean? So רש"י
Rashi says, ah, because it was a מסורה mesorah that came through
the נביאים, Neviim, that they had נבואה. nevuah. So תוספות Tosafos says
you shouldn't have said that, because הלכה halacha is not about נבואה.
nevuah. So when we say חגי זכריה מלאכי, Chagai Zecharia Malachi, it's
not in their role of נביאים. Neviim. תוספות Tosafos says there are
other times we mention חגי זכריה מלאכי, Chagai Zecharia Malachi, who truly
they were נביאים, Neviim, but only as a way of signaling that
it's a very ancient מסורה, mesorah, but in their role as, you
know, transmitters of the oral tradition, not in their role of getting
דבר השם Devar Hashem through נבואה. nevuah. That's irrelevant in the halachic
discussion. So תוספות, Tosafos, it's very important, he rejects רש"י's Rashi attempt
to connect this to נבואה, nevuah, but he says what it does
reflect is that there's an ancient מסורה mesorah about this. So basically
he says it's not that there's a סברא svara and I can
say let me figure out the reasonings and decide who's right. In
the end, it's based on מסורה mesorah and there are different traditions.
And how do I know whose tradition is right? Because it's no
longer about סברא svara and it's just about facts, who has the
right tradition. So therefore I can't decide, so therefore we say we
have to treat אלול Elul separately.
Now, although he should have decided, he could
have decided would have been the מסורה, mesorah, so two final points
about this and then move on. Number one is first of all
this goes against the רמב"ם, Rambam, who insists, the רמב"ם Rambam is
very bothered you know because one of the way the Karaites attacked
the whole תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh notion is he says
how could you you know say that you have the honest tradition
if you have all these debates? Obviously there's been a loss of
transmission so we can't trust anything. So because of that critique, the
רמב"ם Rambam went out of his way to say that all the
debates in the גמרא Gemara are based on the use of the
דרשות drashos to derive laws, and if they're deriving them through the
human intellect there's obviously going to be difference of opinions, but things
that were direct מסורה mesorah were never debated. So he claims that
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai and things that were direct מסורה
mesorah and only were transmitted were never debated. So there's a lot
of evidence against that. There's clearly evidence where they debate הלכה למשה
מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. Here's another area where there's debates about what
the מסורה mesorah was. That's point number one. Point number two is
again going back to this issue about make up your mind. The
רמב"ם Rambam actually incorporates this when he says, you know, like when
we say ספק דאורייתא לחומרא, safek d'oraisa l'chumra, ספק דרבנן לקולא, safek
d'rabanan l'kula, he says that's only if the פוסק posek cannot come
to a determination. Then you go to those principles of how to
deal with ספק. safek. But your first obligation is to try to
work through the reasoning and come up with a פסק הלכה. psak
halacha. So I think this גמרא Gemara is like a nice distillation
of that idea. Okay, so let's now take continue: תניא, Tanya, we
taught in the ברייתא: Braisa: באיזה צד אמר בן עזאי הללו מתעשרין
לעצמן? Be'eizeh tzad amar Ben Azzai halalu mitasrin l'atzman? In what way
did he say that you do them by themselves? Now some, this
phrase באיזה צד be'eizeh tzad appears in the next משנה Mishnah as
well. If you look at the side גרסאות girsa'os they try to
switch it to כיצד. keitzad. Now that's actually interesting because באיזה צד
be'eizeh tzad is actually the earlier form of the word כיצד. keitzad.
Okay, and in משניות Mishnayos that date from an earlier period, you
actually get the phrase באיזה צד be'eizeh tzad in what way. And
באיזה צד be'eizeh tzad later becomes contracted to the word כיצד. keitzad.
Okay, so when they amend this, what they're just doing is fixing
the early language for late language, but this actually proves, you know,
this is an indication of it as an early text when it's
using that phrase באיזה צד. be'eizeh tzad. Okay, so באיזה צד אמר
בן עזאי הללו מתעשרין לעצמן? be'eizeh tzad amar Ben Azzai halalu mitasrin
l'atzman? In what way did he say you take it by themselves?
חמישה באב וחמישה באלול, Chamishah b'Av v'chamishah b'Elul, you had five in
אב, Av, five in אלול, Elul, אין מצטרפין, ein mitstarfin, you don't
combine them. חמישה באלול וחמישה בתשרי, Chamishah b'Elul v'chamishah b'Tishrei, five in
אלול, Elul, five in תשרי, Tishrei, אין מצטרפין, ein mitstarfin, you don't
combine them. חמישה בתשרי וחמישה באב. Chamishah b'Tishrei v'chamishah b'Av. Now if
you have five in תשרי Tishrei and five in אב, Av, so
מצטרפין, mitstarfin, you do combine them, but that's in the same year,
meaning not אב, Av, אלול, Elul, תשרי. Tishrei. You don't go over
the bridge of אלול, Elul, but if it's תשרי, Tishrei, eleven
months and then אב, Av, that's within the same year and that
מצטרפין mitstarfin you do combine.
Again, so although a גורן goren is a period of taking מעשר
בהמה, ma'aser beheimah, here I want to repeat the important הלכה: halacha:
the difference between a גורן goren and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is
that now it's the גורן, goren, I have eighteen animals. So I
go through the process, but I have eight left over. Those eight
will combine with what gets born in the next גורן goren period
and I'm going to have to take it again. But once you
get to the dividing line of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, if there's
eight left over, that's the end. You know, it's sort of like
whether those flex days or whatever, you know, you use it or
lose it. So if you haven't done them by that dividing line...
They don't get pass over that line. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, obvious, this is all obvious. No, מהו דתימא
כי היכי דמפסקי שנים מפסקי גורנות. mahu d'teima ki heichi d'mafski shanim
mafseki goronot.
Exactly this point, I might have thought that the same way the
ראש השנה Rosh Hashana is a dividing line and you don't combine
before and after, so even these גורנות, goronot, these other periods, you
don't go before and after and you don't combine from what's left
over. קא משמע לן kamashmalan that you do. כדתנן, kitnan, just like
we taught in our משנה: Mishnah: חמישה לפני ראש השנה וחמישה לאחר
ראש השנה אין מצטרפין. chamisha lifnei Rosh Hashana v'chamisha l'achar Rosh Hashana
ein mitztarfin. Five before and five after they don't combine. חמישה לפני
הגורן וחמישה לאחר הגורן, chamisha lifnei hagoren v'chamisha l'achar hagoren, five that
were leftover or you even only had five before the one of
the other, you know, גורן goren periods, and five that were born
after, הרי אלו מצטרפין harei elu mitztarfin they do combine. This brings
up an interesting point.
It might be kind of hard to keep track of that. Like,
you have a flock of a thousand animals, you have five left
over, how are you gonna know which of those five
were the ones that were left over? It's a good point. You
maybe put some, I don't know,
yellow, yeah, you'd have to figure that out. אמר רבא. Amar Rava.
So רבא Rava said, לדברי בן עזאי, l'divrei Ben Azzai, now I
was waiting for Michael to ask this question. Okay, here's the obvious
question to ask. There could be a scenario where you ודאי vadai
have to take מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah, but you don't know how.
לדברי בן עזאי נולדו לו חמישה באב חמישה באלול וחמישה בתשרי. l'divrei
Ben Azzai noldu lo chamisha b'Av chamisha b'Elul v'chamisha b'Tishrei. Five in
אב, Av, five in אלול, Elul, five in תשרי. Tishrei. However, wherever
you draw that dividing line, you're going to get ten because the
אלול Elul will either combine with before or with after, but you
just don't know which ten to take מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah on.
So how are you going to deal with that? כונסן לדיר לעשר,
Konsan l'dir l'atzer, put them all in the, you put them all
in a, you know, pen, ונוטל אחד מהלו, v'notel echad meihalu, and
you make sure, we'll talk about in a minute how you make
sure, that the מעשר ma'aser you take is from one of those
born on אלול. Elul. So then it doesn't matter whether they combine
before or after, the five in אלול Elul are definitely part of
the מעשר. ma'aser. And therefore, as long as you take one from
those, you know you are taking from an animal that's obligated in
מעשר. ma'aser. והשאר פטורין ממה נפשך, v'hashar pturin maman nafshach, and the
rest are anyway exempt. אם אחד באלול ראש השנה, im echad b'Elul
Rosh Hashana,
if the first day of אלול Elul is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana,
דאלול ותשרי מצטרפין, d'Elul v'Tishrei mitztarfin, so אלול Elul and תשרי Tishrei
combine, ודאב פטורין v'dei-Av pturin and the אב Av are exempt. ואם
אחד בתשרי ראש השנה, ve'im echad b'Tishrei Rosh Hashana, if ראש השנה
Rosh Hashana תשרי Tishrei is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, אמרת
לצרופו, amarta litzrufu, I'm sorry, דאב ואלול מצטרפין, d'Av v'Elul mitztarfin, so
what comes in אב Av and אלול Elul combine, דתשרי פטורין d'Tishrei
pturin and תשרי Tishrei is exempt. מאי אמרת? Mah amarta? What do
you want to suggest? לצרופו לגורן אחר? Litzrufu l'goren acher? Maybe, here's
the only question: if the ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, if ראש השנה
Rosh Hashana was תשרי, Tishrei, then the five born in תשרי Tishrei
maybe were not part of the מעשר ma'aser count and have to
combine with the stuff that came after תשרי, Tishrei, right? So how
do I say now that I've combined this whole thing, combined אב,
Av, אלול, Elul, and תשרי Tishrei to take one מעשר? ma'aser? I
can't just say I've solved the whole problem because if the dividing
line was תשרי, Tishrei, those five in תשרי Tishrei have to combine
with stuff that comes later and I'm going to say that they're
exempt. Says that doesn't matter because
עשירי ודאי אמר רחמנא ולא ספק, asiri vadai amar Rachmana v'lo safek,
because the רחמנא Rachmana says only thing that you're definitely obligated. And
this also explains the question that was asked that בן עזאי Ben
Azzai is a קולא. kula. Yes, בן עזאי Ben Azzai is a
קולא. kula. But if he really has a ספק, safek, then the
הלכה halacha is is that once there's a doubt, you're not obligated
to take מעשר ma'aser on stuff that there's a doubt of. So
what that means according to בן עזאי Ben Azzai is when you
have this five, five, and five, and then you take your מעשר
ma'aser in that case, is the five from תשרי Tishrei in doubt
whether you've done your מצוה mitzvah or not? Yes. But once you've
created that doubt or once that doubt exists, you don't then they're
out of the category for מעשר. ma'aser. So the גמרא Gemara says
פשיטא? pshita? Isn't all of this obvious? No, מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima,
I might have thought לגזור ligzor let's make a גזירה, gzira, דילמא
אתי למשקל מהנך, dilma atei lemishkal meihannach, we don't let you do
this whole process because you might accidentally not take from the five
of אלול. Elul. You might take from the others and right if
you take from the others they're not necessarily obligated in מעשר, ma'aser,
right? If you have the אב, Av, אלול, Elul, תשרי Tishrei and
you do it and you forget to take from the אלול Elul
ones and you take from a תשרי Tishrei one, well maybe you
took from an animal that's not obligated in מעשר ma'aser because maybe
it was only אב Av and אלול, Elul, right? And vice versa.
So maybe I should make a גזירה gzira that you won't be
careful and make sure to take from the אלול. Elul. קא משמע
לן Kamashmalan that we're not concerned about that. So here's what you
have this important principle of number one, מעשר ודאי ולא מעשר ספק,
ma'aser vadai v'lo ma'aser safek, which will play out also in the
next משנה. mishnah. And that means that you know why don't you
say why how can בן עזאי Ben Azzai say which was Charlie's
question, oh, take אלול Elul by itself? What do you mean? Maybe
we should be מחמיר machmir both ways, essentially we're being מקל meikel
both ways. And the answer is you can't be מחמיר machmir in
a מקום ספק makom safek by מעשר. ma'aser. Once there's a ספק,
safek, the anything that's under the ספק safek you're exempt. Okay, so
therefore you have to do the אלול Elul by itself, anything left
over before or anything after is the מקום ספק. makom safek. The
only time that you would do it is when it combine either
way you go will combine and then you do it through this
way in the גמרא.
Gemara. Last אלול Elul opposed to this coming אלול, Elul, you know?
Right. You still could've gone to said it the other way. You
know you said you do five from אב, Av, five from אלול,
Elul, five from תשרי, Tishrei, you're still putting this תשרי Tishrei with
the last אלול Elul maybe you're supposed to do it with the
following.
I understand, but right now, right now you know that amongst these
fifteen animals you're חייב chayiv in מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. So there's
no ספק safek to take מעשר בהמה ma'aser behemah it's just about
which ones combine. So you have to deal with that scenario. Now,
I did want to make one more point and then I'll get
to the משנה Mishnah which is how can you make sure to
take it from those from אלול? Elul? Normally we say that you're
not... not manipulate it. It says לא יבקר בין טוב לרע, lo
yivaker bein tov l'ra, that you cannot select good or bad which
basically is understood to mean not just good or bad, but you
can't manipulate which one comes out tenth. So how here can we
tell you take from the ones that are in אלול? Elul? So
רש"י Rashi says as we're going to learn in the next משנה
mishnah that even though you're supposed to have them walk out single
file from the door in the pen, that if you בדיעבד, b'di'eved,
if you actually they were all just standing there and you actually
just counted them yourself, one, two, three, four, five, whatever, that works.
So if you actually are not manipulating which one comes out tenth,
apparently it's not לא יבקר lo yivaker if you're not manipulating how
they come out, but you're just making sure how you count. Okay,
you could say that's also לא יבקר, lo yivaker, you're making sure
to come around. I also don't know according to רש"י Rashi what
would you do? Would you have to count ten twice? Meaning you
start here at תשרי, Tishrei, you go one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, and then you end eight, nine, ten with the אלול.
Elul.
Then you start here with
the אב Av and you do the same thing, eight, nine, ten
with the אלול. Elul. Maybe you have to do that. Okay, but
anyway רש"י Rashi says as long as you're not manipulating which one
comes out, even though you're planning, it's sort of like the eeny-meeny-miny-moe
thing, you know, if you're smart you could sort of plan how
it's going to come out. Okay, so you plan how it's going
to come out. תוספות Tosafot just says simply oh that doesn't apply
here. And it could be what תוספות Tosafot's point is is that
it doesn't apply because it's necessary since I'm obligated in מעשר, ma'aser,
there's no other way of doing מעשר, ma'aser, therefore it's there, you
know, therefore it's not that sense of intentionally selecting because it's what's
necessary to be done in order to fulfill the מצוה mitzvah of
מעשר. ma'aser. But that is a question that the גמרא Gemara does
not directly address. Let's take a look now at the next משנה.
mishnah.
באיזה צד מעשרין, B'eizeh tzad m'asrin, again if the sides try to
change it to כיצד, k'eitzad, but that's the earlier form here. The
earlier form is באיזה צד. b'eizeh tzad. How do you do the
מעשר? ma'aser? Actually not just the periods of the year, but the
act of taking the מעשר. ma'aser. כונסן לדיר ועושה פתח קטן, Kunsam
l'dir v'osem petach katan, you put them all in a pen, you
make a little opening, כדי שלא שנים יכולים לצאת כאחד, k'dei shelo
shnayim yecholim latzeit k'echad,
so that it only can go out single file. Two can't come
out at once because obviously that will confuse it. ומונין U'monin and
you count, א ב ג ד ה ו ז ח ט, aleph
bet gimmel dalet hey vav zayin chet tet, right? והיוצא עשירי V'hayotzei
asiri and
the one that comes out tenth, סוקרו בסיקרא, soker b'sikra,
you paint it with paint, ואומר הרי זה מעשר, v'omer harei zeh
ma'aser,
and you say that this is מעשר. ma'aser. לא
סקרו בסיקרא, Lo sakro b'sikra, you didn't, now again, so הרי זה
מעשר harei zeh ma'aser sounds like you're actually being מקדיש makdish it,
going back to תוספות Tosafot's point. Okay, but you might not have
to actually say that, meaning you might just say this is ten,
not I'm מקדיש makdish this as מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. Okay, so
that's an interesting question as we said, is it enough to designate
it as ten, which is what תוספות Tosafot has, or do you
have to actually say it was עשר, eser, not מעשר? ma'aser? So
that's why there's a little not so clear, or do you actually
have to sanctify it as מעשר? ma'aser? Okay. לא סקרו בסיקרא, Lo
sakro b'sikra, you did not use the paint, ולא מנאן בשבט, v'lo
m'na'an b'shevet, and you didn't count them with the staff, one, two,
three. You know, maybe you were visually counting, but you didn't do
the paint, it was all just in your head. Okay. או שמנאן
רבוצים או עומדים, O she'm'na'an revutzim o omdim, this is what רש"י
Rashi said, or you didn't have them go through the door at
all, you just counted one, two, three, four, five and they were
all crouching or standing. Okay. הרי אלו מתעשרין, Harei elu mit'asrin, then
that still works. So you're supposed to, you're supposed to count out
loud, you're supposed to have them walk single file, but even if
they didn't do any of that, you just counted in your head,
then that also works.
Okay. You have problems, I mean if you, you know, if you
didn't even paint it, how are you going to know which was
your tenth?
Okay, you'll have to deal with that, but as in terms of
whether you're יוצא מעשר, yotzei ma'aser, it works. היה לו מאה ונטל
עשרה עשרה, Hayah lo me'ah v'natal asarah asarah, let's say you had
a hundred and you took groups of ten, ונטל אחד, v'natal echad,
אין זה מעשר. ein zeh ma'aser. You didn't do any counting, you
just said ten, okay, this one's מעשר. ma'aser. Here's another ten, that
one's מעשר. ma'aser. There was no, there was no counting, not even
counting in your head. It was just taking one out of every
ten, that doesn't work. It's not enough to take one out of
ten, there has to be some
counting although בדיעבד b'di'eved it can all be in your head.
I don't understand, it was like the whole,
why are you doing that? I mean in other words if you,
it works
like because first of all it's easier, it saves you time, and
number two, it works in, it's the same way you would take
מעשר ma'aser by grain. מעשר ma'aser by grain you would just take
out the מעשר. ma'aser. So by the analogy to the grain, fine,
I'll take one out of ten. That's the most natural thing. No,
no, I'm saying why doesn't it work?
That's my question.
Oh, because they learn about, about כל אשר יעבור תחת השבט העשירי.
kol asher ya'avor tachat hashevet ha'asiri. Okay, so they understand that there's
an עניין inyan of being, so somehow they learn יעבור תחת השבט
ya'avor tachat hashevet is not מעכב, m'akev, but העשירי, ha'asiri, there's an
idea of being the tenth. It doesn't say take ten percent, it
says the tenth. So you can only be the tenth if there
was nine counted beforehand. Yes.
Does the tenth group though be all מעשר? ma'aser?
That's interesting, I don't think so though, I think maybe, I don't
know, I doubt it. Okay. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר מעשר. Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Yehudah omer ma'aser. He says no, that actually does work
as long as it's one out of ten, even if it's not
the tenth, it still works. Now, קפץ אחד מן המנונים לתוכן, kafatz
echad min ham'nunim l'tochan, this is a very famous גמרא Gemara for
anybody who learned בבא מציעא Bava Metzia משנה, mishnah, if one of
the ones you already counted jumped back in to the mix. Now
you have a problem because you can't double count anything. So now
anyone that walks out might be one of the ones that's already
counted and it can't be double counted and that'll set all the
numbering off, right? Because if it's the... If it's one that's already
counted, so what that winds up doing is it gets you out
of all of it gets you out of continuing. הרי אלו פטורים,
harei elu pturim, now they're all זה, zeh, now they're all מעשר
ספק maaser safek and מעשר ספק maaser safek you don't take as
soon as there's any doubt. So one of them jumps in whether
it was a black sheep or whether it was a white sheep?
No, obviously you don't know. Why wouldn't you just start over counting
again?
What? Until you've counted ten, you haven't done anything significant.
No, so so we'll see in the גמרא Gemara that that's not
true. That actually once they've been counted, they've been exempt as soon
as they've been part of the count, even if nothing else has
happened. And then if they jump back, it creates a ספק safek
with everything else. And the principle is מעשר ודאי, maaser vadai, not
מעשר ספק. maaser safek.
And
it has to
be counted with the
intent for מעשר, maaser,
I presume, not
just counting my sheep. Yes, yes. מן המעושר, mina hamsusar,
yeah. מן המעושר. mina hamsusar. Now let's say one of the מעשר
maaser ones you didn't paint it. There's a reason to paint. It
gets jumps back in. Not only are they all exempt, but also
now you've got a problem because any one of them might be
מעשר, maaser, any one of them might be מעשר maaser and you're
not allowed to eat מעשר maaser without outside of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash without bringing it as a קרבן. korban. So now what
do you do? Not only are they exempt, but any one might
be מעשר. maaser. So ירעו עד שיסתאבו ויאכלו במומם לבעלים. yirehu ad
sheyistavlu veyochlu bemumam labaalim. Or you could go up to ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. בהקדש behekdesh of them
you could.
Okay, so Michael's like you could be מקדיש maktish all of them
בתנאי. bitnai. But yeah,
Tzvi is going to remind us that the way you do the
דם dam is different. Anyway, the easier thing is that you wait
for them to get a blemish and then you eat them all
out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but you have to treat all of them
with ספק קדושת מעשר. safek kedushas maaser. So that creates a real
hardship. So it's really smart to use the paint. Okay, let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tano rabanan. באיזה צד
מעשר? Be'ezeh tzad maaser? באיזה צד מעשר? Be'ezeh tzad maaser? How do
you do מעשר? maaser? There's a ברייתא braisa parallel to our משנה.
mishna. כונסן לדיר ועושה להם פתח קטן konesam ladir veoseh lahem pesach
katan כדי שלא יהיו שנים יכולים לצאת כאחד, kedei shelo yehu shnayim
yecholim latzeis k'echad,
so that only they can only go out single file, two can't
go out at once. אמותיהם מבחוץ imoseihem mibachutz
and you have the mothers on the outside of the pen, והם
מבפנים, veheim mibifnim, they're on the inside, וגועות, vegayos, and the mothers
are braying, or you know, והן יוצאות לקראת אמן vehein yotzos likras
imon
and they go out to their mother. So that's the incentive for
them to come out, so that's you know, using the carrot rather
than the stick.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says: ולפקינהו אינהו? velivkinu inu?
Why don't you just take them out physically yourself? One, two, etc.
You know, pick them up and take them out. No, יעבור סיק,
yaavor sik, they should pass under the staff. They have to be
walking on their own. So it says: ולא שיעבירוהו, velo sheyaaviruhu, not
that other people take them out. ולישדי להו ירקא וליפקו? velishdi lehu
yarca velepku? Why not just throw them some vegetables outside of the
pen? Chow time. It's almost as good as mommy, right? So they'll
come out because they want the food. So the גמרא Gemara says:
וליפקו אבתריה velepku abasrei and they'll come out to you. אמר רב
הונא: Amar Rav Huna: גזירה משום לקוח משום יתום gzeira mishum lakuach
mishum yasom because of a concern of things that are purchased or
orphaned. Remember, you don't take מעשר maaser from animals that are purchased
and you don't take מעשר maaser from animals that their mothers died
at the moment of childbirth. So therefore, if you use the mothers,
so the ones that don't have mothers, you can't do that trick
for. Now that assumes that you have animals braying and moms braying,
that the sheep are not going to follow all the other sheep,
which they probably will, even if it's not their particular mother. So
you don't have to say that means that they won't go out,
but what you could say is better, that the use of mothers
is a reminder to you that it's only things that were born
to your own flock, not things you purchased. Things you purchased,
normally you'll purchase the sheep straight, not with its mother. And not
things that the mother died during childbirth. So it's a signal to
you. It signals to you to remember that these are only sheep
that were born to your flock and not sheep that you purchased
and not sheep that the mother died at childbirth. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן. Tano rabanan. כל אשר יעבור
תחת השבט. Kol asher yaavor tachat hashevet. כל אשר יעבור, Kol asher
yaavor, פרט לטריפה שאינו עובר. prat l'treifa she'eino over.
First of all, this excludes טריפה treifa as you learned yesterday, that
an example of טריפה treifa is an animal with a missing leg.
So therefore, somehow, again it's you know, of course תוספות Tosafot points
out you could be missing a leg and not be a טריפה
treifa in a lower leg and not be a טריפה, treifa, but
anyway they learned from that idea that it has to be in
the category of animals that pass under and טריפות treifas are excluded.
תחת השבט. Tachat hashevet. Now the staff.
מצוה למנאם בשבט. Mitzvah limnosam beshevet. Now here's where you get the
idea of a מצוה, mitzvah, it's not מעכב, me'akev, and that the
question is how do we know that it's not absolutely necessary? But
nevertheless, לכתחילה lechatchila you're supposed to actually have them go under a
staff and use the staff to count them. And as Rivka says,
it's exactly that image of מעביר צאן תחת שבטו, maavir tzon tachat
shivto, exactly this. לא מנאם בשבט, Lo manam beshevet, if you didn't
use your staff, או שמנאם רבוצים או עומדים, o shemanam revutzim o
omdim, or you didn't even have them walk, you just counted them
when they were standing or sitting. מניין? Minayin? How do you know
that works? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: העשירי קודש מכל מקום, ha'asiri kodesh
mikol makom, the tenth one. So they learn out that that means
even if you didn't do that as long as it was the
tenth, that's enough. But it doesn't mean ten percent, it has to
be the tenth. So you don't have to have them walk, you
don't have to use your staff בדיעבד, b'diavad, לכתחילה l'chatchila you do,
it's a מצוה mitzvah to do it, but as long as you
counted them in your mind and this was number ten, not just
not just one out of ten, but number ten, the tenth, that's
enough. ואין לי אלא שקרא שמו עשירי, V'ein li ela she-kara shemo
asiri, I only know that you actually verbalize and say ten, and
notice here it doesn't say מעשר, maaser, it says ten, going back
to that question of is it enough to designate it as ten.
לא קרא שמו עשירי מנין, Lo kara shemo asiri minayin, if you
had only in your head you were thinking it was tenth, but
you didn't actually verbalize it, how do I know? תלמוד לומר יהיה
קודש מכל מקום, Talmud lomar yiheyeh kodesh mikol makom, even it's regardless,
even if you don't count it and designate it as ten. So
it has to be the tenth, but that's enough that it's totally
in your head, you don't even have to designate it. One minute.
יכול היו לו מאה ונטל עשרה עשרה ונטל אחד יכול יהיו מעושרים,
Yachol hayu lo meah v'natal asarah asarah v'natal echad yachol yiheyu meusarin,
maybe if maybe if I just took one out of every ten
it's enough without being the tenth, but just being one out of
ten, maybe that's enough? תלמוד לומר עשירי, Talmud lomar asiri, it has
to be tenth, ואין זה עשירי, v'ein zeh asiri, this is not
the tenth, this is one out of ten, it's ten percent, but
it's not the tenth. So לכתחילה l'chatchila count, have them walk, use
a staff, etc.
בדיעבד b'diavad anything that is even if you did it in your
head and even if as long as it is the tenth and
not ten percent, it's enough. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר מעשר, Rabbi
Yosi b'Rabbi Yehuda omer maaser, that does work. Now מאי טעמא דרבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, mai taama d'Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Yehuda, what's his reasoning?
סבירא ליה כאבא אלעזר בן גומל Savira lei k'Abba Elazar ben Gomel
or גומל Gomel or גמלא Gamla in other גרסאות, girsaot, דתניא אבא
אלעזר בן גומל אומר ונחשב לכם תרומתכם, d'tanya Abba Elazar ben Gomel
omer v'nechshav lachem trumatchem, this is talking about taking תרומת מעשר trumat
maaser ten percent, and it says and it compares it to normal
תרומה. trumah. בשתי תרומות הכתוב מדבר אחת תרומה גדולה ואחת תרומת מעשר,
Bishtei trumot hakatuv medaber achat trumah gedolah v'achat trumat maaser, whether the
normal תרומה trumah you take which is like one or two percent,
whether it's תרומת מעשר trumat maaser which is ten percent that the
לויים Levi'im take and give to the כהנים Kohanim from their
מעשר. maaser. כשם שתרומה גדולה ניטלת באומד ובמחשבה, K'shem she-trumah gedolah nitelet
b'omed u-v'machshavah, so
אף תרומת מעשר ניטלת באומד ובמחשבה. af trumat maaser nitelet b'omed u-v'machshavah.
So we'll finish this tomorrow, but the basic point is like this,
that תרומה trumah you can take just in your head and therefore
you can take תרומת מעשר trumat maaser in your head, and what
we're going to say is if you can take תרומה trumah and
תרומת מעשר trumat maaser in your head, you can also take מעשר
maaser and מעשר בהמה maaser behemah in your head. And since you
so he says since you can do it by grain, you can
do it all in your head, here you can do all in
your head, but not only in your head, but without making it
the tenth. The way מעשר maaser is taken is ten percent, so
here too by the בהמה, behemah, as long as it's one out
of ten, even without being the tenth, for his position that is
sufficient. So we will continue with this tomorrow.
I only know that you actually verbalize and say
ten.